Susan Vanderplas

802 17th St., Auburn, NE 68305 o (515) 509-6613 srvanderplas@gmail.com

About me I am a data engineer, that is, I transform data into informed decisions by building and interpreting mathematical models. I work with subject matter experts to understand and quantify prior knowledge, then incorporate data to create robust, accurate predictive models. These skills can be applied to variables such as day-ahead and real-time markets, network congestion, load balancing, megawatt valuation, and rate outlook, which I believe will greatly benefit NPPD.

Education

Iowa State University

2015 - Ph.D. in Statistics; GPA 3.71 2011 - M.S. Statistics; GPA 3.69

Texas A&M University

2009 - B.S. Psychology and Applied Mathematics; GPA 3.88

Skills

Statistical Techniques

- Estimation
- Prediction (with error bounds)
- Multivariate modeling

Computer Skills

- R (statistical programming)
- SAS statistical software
- Interactive dashboard design

- Risk assessment
- Reliability analysis
- Time Dependent models
- C, C++
- JavaScript
- Software development

- Monte Carlo methods
- "Big Data" analysis
- Market Test design
- Database design (SQL)
- Microsoft Office
- Windows and Linux

Experience

Industrial Statistics 2012-2015

- Estimated capacity factor and number of maintenance issues for an industrial site, compensating for a longer length between maintenance cycles. Accurately predicted the number of maintenance outages that occurred during the first 24-month cycle using 18-month cycle data.
- Assembled locational marginal price data from several regional transmission operators to examine the financial impact of scheduling power plant maintenance on weekends and holidays and explore the conditions leading to negative power prices.

Cross-discipline collaboration (with materials engineering)

2010-2011

Increased accuracy and efficiency of peak detection (vs. manual identification) using robust quantile analysis.

Iowa Department of Transportation

2012

Examined the effect of road layout and construction on driver safety (collisions, fatalities).

USDA Soybean Genome Project

2013 - 2015

Built models and interactive web applications to explore the influence of genetic mutations on soybean yield.

Postdoc, Iowa State Office of Vice President for Research

2015

Evaluated ROI and profitability of funding models for faculty research.

Google Summer of Code

Summer 2013, 2014, 2015

Worked on development of a software package to create interactive web graphics using R, and returned to serve as a mentor for the project in 2014 and 2015.